Suppose you're left to decide what degree of polynomial to fit to a data set.
データセットに
So that what features to include that gives you a learning algorithm.
何次の多項式まで含めて
Or suppose you'd like to choose the regularization parameter longer for
フィットさせたいか決めたい、としよう。
learning algorithm.
つまり学習アルゴリズムになんのフィーチャーを含めるか、という話だ。
How do you do that?
または学習アルゴリズムの正規化パラメータ、ラムダを
This account model selection process.
選びたいとしよう。
Browsers, and in our discussion of how to do this, we'll talk about not just how to
どうやる？
split your data into the train and test sets, but how to switch data into what we
これらはモデル選択問題と呼ばれている。
discover is called the train, validation, and test sets.
これをどう行うかの議論をするにあたり、
We'll see in this video just what these things are, and
データをどうトレーニングセットと
how to use them to do model selection.
テストセットに
We've already seen a lot of times the problem of overfitting,
分割するかだけでなく、
in which just because a learning algorithm fits a training set well,
データを、
that doesn't mean it's a good hypothesis.
やがて見る事になる、
More generally, this is why the training set's error is not a good predictor for
トレインバリデーションと呼ばれる物と
how well the hypothesis will do on new example.
テストセットにデータをどう分割するかを扱う。
Concretely, if you fit some set of parameters.
このビデオの中で
Theta0, theta1, theta2, and so on, to your training set.
以上の事がいったいなんなのか、
Then the fact that your hypothesis does well on the training set.
そしてそれらを使ってどうモデル選択をするかを見ていく。
Well, this doesn't mean much in terms of predicting how well your hypothesis will
ここまでに何度も
generalize to new examples not seen in the training set.
オーバーフィティングの問題を見てきた。
And a more general principle is that once your
そこでは学習アルゴリズムが
parameter is what fit to some set of data.
トレーニングセットに良くフィットしているからといって
Maybe the training set, maybe something else.
必ずしも良い仮説だとは限らないのだった。
Then the error of your hypothesis as measured on that same data set,
より一般的には、これこそが
such as the training error,
トレーニングセットの誤差が
that's unlikely to be a good estimate of your actual generalization error.
新しいサンプルに対してどれだけ
That is how well the hypothesis will generalize to new examples.
良い予測器かの良い指標にはならない理由だった。
Now let's consider the model selection problem.
具体的には、
Let's say you're trying to choose what degree polynomial to fit to data.
あるパラメータの集まり、
So, should you choose a linear function, a quadratic function, a cubic function?
シータ0、シータ1、シータ2など、
All the way up to a 10th-order polynomial.
をトレーニングセットにフィットしようと
So it's as if there's one extra parameter in this algorithm,
しているとしよう。
which I'm going to denote d, which is, what degree of polynomial.
その時に仮説がトレーニングセットに対して
Do you want to pick.
良いという事実は、
So it's as if, in addition to the theta parameters, it's as if
仮説が新たな、トレーニングセットに無い
there's one more parameter, d, that you're trying to determine using your data set.
サンプルをどれだけうまく予言するかという
So, the first option is d equals one, if you fit a linear function.
観点からは、
We can choose d equals two, d equals three, all the way up to d equals 10.
多くは
So, we'd like to fit this extra sort of parameter which I'm denoting by d.
意味しない、という事。
And concretely let's say that you want to choose a model,
より一般的な原則としては、
that is choose a degree of polynomial, choose one of these 10 models.
一旦パラメータをあるデータの集合に
And fit that model and also get some estimate of how well your
フィッティングしたら、
fitted hypothesis was generalize to new examples.
それがトレーニングセットであれそれ以外であれ、
Here's one thing you could do.
その同じデータセットに対して
What you could, first take your first model and minimize the training error.
測った仮説の誤差というのは、
And this would give you some parameter vector theta.
たとえばトレーニング誤差などは
And you could then take your second model, the quadratic function, and
それは恐らく
fit that to your training set and this will give you some other.
実際の一般のケースの誤差を
Parameter vector theta.
推計するには良い物では無い。
In order to distinguish between these different parameter vectors, I'm going
つまりどれだけ仮説が
to use a superscript one superscript two there where theta superscript one
新しいサンプルに対してうまく一般化されているか、という事については。
just means the parameters I get by fitting this model to my training data.
では、モデル選択問題を検討してみよう。
And theta superscript two just means the parameters I
データをフィットするのに、 何次の多項式を
get by fitting this quadratic function to my training data and so on.
含めるかを選ぼうとしている、としよう。
By fitting a cubic model I get parenthesis three up to, well, say theta 10.
つまり、あなたは線形関数を選びたい、
And one thing we ccould do is that take these parameters and look at test error.
二次関数、三次関数、
So I can compute on my test set J test of one,
、、、と10乗の多項式まで。
J test of theta two, and so on.
つまり、それはまるで、一つ追加のパラメータ、
J test of theta three, and so on.
それをdで表すが、
So I'm going to take each of my hypotheses with the corresponding parameters and
何次の多項式まで含めるか、を表す
just measure the performance of on the test set.
パラメータがアルゴリズムにあるみたいな物だ。
Now, one thing I could do then is, in order to select one of these models,
つまりまるで、
I could then see which model has the lowest test set error.
パラメータのシータに追加して
And let's just say for
さらにもう一つ、
this example that I ended up choosing the fifth order polynomial.
パラメータdという物が
So, this seems reasonable so far.
追加されていて、それをデータセットを用いて決めたい、と考える。
But now let's say I want to take my fifth hypothesis, this, this,
最初の選択肢はd=1で
fifth order model, and let's say I want to ask, how well does this model generalize?
それは線形関数となる。
One thing I could do is look at how well my fifth order
d=2も、d=3も、、、と
polynomial hypothesis had done on my test set.
d=10までの
But the problem is this will not be a fair estimate of how well my
選択肢がある。
hypothesis generalizes.
つまりこの、ある意味で追加のパラメータについて
And the reason is what we've done is we've fit this extra parameter d,
フィッティングしたい、という訳だ。
that is this degree of polynomial.
それをdで示していて、
And what fits that parameter d, using the test set, namely,
具体的には、
we chose the value of d that gave us the best possible performance on the test set.
モデルを選びたいと、
And so, the performance of my parameter vector theta5, on the test set,
これら10個のモデルから
that's likely to be an overly optimistic estimate of generalization error.
一つの多項式の次数を選びたいとする。
Right, so, that because I had fit this parameter d to my test set is no longer
そしてそのモデルをフィッティングして
fair to evaluate my hypothesis on this test set, because I fit my parameters
そのフィッティングした仮説が
to this test set, I've chose the degree d of polynomial using the test set.
どれくらいうまく、
And so my hypothesis is likely to do better on
新しいサンプルに対して一般化されているかを
this test set than it would on new examples that it hasn't seen before, and
評価する。
that's which is, which is what I really care about.
一つ、ありえる事としては、こんなのがある:
So just to reiterate, on the previous slide, we saw that if we fit some set of
最初のモデルを取って
parameters, you know, say theta0, theta1, and so on, to some training set,
トレーニング誤差を最小化し、
then the performance of the fitted model on the training set is not predictive of
それであるパラメータベクトルが
how well the hypothesis will generalize to new examples.
得られる。
Is because these parameters were fit to the training set,
そして次に、二番目のモデル、二次関数を
so they're likely to do well on the training set,
とってきて、
even if the parameters don't do well on other examples.
トレーニングセットに対してーー
And, in the procedure I just described on this line, we just did the same thing.
別のパラメータベクトル、シータを得る事になる。
And specifically, what we did was, we fit this parameter d to the test set.
これら別々のパラメータベクトルを
And by having fit the parameter to the test set, this means that
区別する為に、
the performance of the hypothesis on that test set may not be a fair estimate of how
下付き添字1、2、、、を使っていく。
well the hypothesis is, is likely to do on examples we haven't seen before.
ここでシータの下付き添字1は、
To address this problem, in a model selection setting,
このモデルをトレーニングデータに対して
if we want to evaluate a hypothesis, this is what we usually do instead.
フィッティングして
Given the data set, instead of just splitting into a training test set,
得られたパラメータを意味するに過ぎない。
what we're going to do is then split it into three pieces.
シータ下付き添字2は単に
And the first piece is going to be called the training set as usual.
この二次関数をトレーニングデータに対して
So let me call this first part the training set.
フィッティングして得られたパラメータを表すだけ、などなど。
And the second piece of this data, I'm going to call the cross validation set.
そして三次のモデルをフィッティングする事で、パラメータ、シータ3を得て、
[SOUND] Cross validation.
これをシータ10まで続ける事が出来る。
And the cross validation, as V-D.
そしてここまて来た後にやれる事としては、一つには
Sometimes it's also called the validation set instead of cross validation set.
これらのパラメータに対し
And then the loss can be to call the usual test set.
テストセットの誤差を見ていく。
And the pretty, pretty typical ratio at which to split these things will be
つまり、テストセットに対して
to send 60% of your data's, your training set,
Jのtestのシータ1、
maybe 20% to your cross validation set, and 20% to your test set.
Jのtestのシータ2、
And these numbers can vary a little bit but this integration be pretty typical.
みたいに。
And so our training sets will now be only maybe 60% of the data, and our
Jのtestのシータ3
cross-validation set, or our validation set, will have some number of examples.
とか。
I'm going to denote that m subscript cv.
つまり、対応する仮説を
So that's the number of cross-validation examples.
一つずつ見ていって
Following our early notational convention I'm going to use xi cv comma y i cv,
テストセットに対するパフォーマンスを
to denote the i cross validation example.
ただ計測していくだけ。
And finally we also have a test set over here with our
そこから出来る事としては、一つには
m subscript test being the number of test examples.
これらのモデルを選ぶ為に
So, now that we've defined the training validation or
どのモデルが
cross validation and test sets.
一番低い
We can also define the training error, cross validation error, and test error.
テストセットの誤差となっているかを見る、
So here's my training error, and
というのがある。
I'm just writing this as J subscript train of theta.
そしてこの例では、仮に
This is pretty much the same things.
5次の多項式を選ぶ事になったとしよう。
These are the same thing as the J of theta that I've been writing so
ここまではリーズナブルっぽいね。
far, this is just a training set error you know, as measuring a training set and then
だがここで、フィットさせた仮説、
J subscript cv my cross validation error, this is pretty much what you'd expect,
この5次のモデルに
just like the training error you've set measure it on a cross validation data set,
対して、このモデルが
and here's my test set error same as before.
どれだけうまく一般化されているか知りたいとする。
So when faced with a model selection problem like this, what we're going to
一つ考えられるのは、
do is, instead of using the test set to select the model, we're instead
五次の多項式の仮説がどれだけテストセットに対して
going to use the validation set, or the cross validation set, to select the model.
うまく機能するかを見る、という事だが、、、
Concretely, we're going to first take our first hypothesis, take this first model,
だがこれには問題がある。
and say, minimize the cross function, and
これは我らの仮説がどれだけうまく
this would give me some parameter vector theta for the new model.
一般化出来ているかを見積もるには
And, as before, I'm going to put a superscript 1,
フェアなやり方じゃないって事だ。
just to denote that this is the parameter for the new model.
その理由は、我らがやった事はそもそも、
We do the same thing for the quadratic model.
この追加のパラメータdを
Get some parameter vector theta two.
それは多項式の次数だが、
Get some para, parameter vector theta three, and so
これをフィッティングたのだった。
on, down to theta ten for the polynomial.
そしてこのdは、
And what I'm going to do is, instead of testing these hypotheses on the test set,
テストセットを使ってフィッティングしたのだった。
I'm instead going to test them on the cross validation set.
ようするに、我らはdの値を
And measure J subscript cv,
テストセットに対して最も高いパフォーマンスが出るように
to see how well each of these hypotheses do on my cross validation set.
選んだのだった。
And then I'm going to pick the hypothesis with the lowest cross validation error.
だから、
So for this example, let's say for the sake of argument,
パラメータベクトルのシータ5の
that it was my 4th order polynomial, that had the lowest cross validation error.
テストセットに対してのパフォーマンスは
So in that case I'm going to pick this fourth order polynomial model.
たぶん一般化の誤差を見積もるには
And finally, what this means is that that parameter d,
過剰に楽観的に
remember d was the degree of polynomial, right?
なってしまうはず。
So d equals two, d equals three, all the way up to d equals 10.
でしょ？だってパラメータdは
What we've done is we'll fit that parameter d and we'll say d equals four.
テストセットに対してフィッティングしたんだから。
And we did so using the cross-validation set.
だからもはや、
And so this degree of polynomial, so the parameter, is no longer fit to the test
仮説をテストセットに対して用いるのは
set, and so we've not saved away the test set, and we can use the test set to
フェアじゃ無くなってしまっているよ。
measure, or to estimate the generalization error of the model that was selected.
だってパラメータのフィッティングにテストセットを使っちゃったんだから。
By the of them.
多項式の次数、dを
So, that was model selection and how you can take your data,
テストセットを使って選んだんだった。
split it into a training, validation, and test set.
だから我らの仮説は
And use your cross validation data to select the model and
たぶんテストセットに対しての方が
evaluate it on the test set.
まだ見ぬ新しいサンプルに対してより
One final note, I should say that in.
うまく振舞ってしまうだろう。
The machine learning, as of this practice today, there aren't many
そしてその新しいサンプルに対してこそが知りたい事だ。
people that will do that early thing that I talked about, and said that, you know,
前のスライドを
it isn't such a good idea, of selecting your model using this test set.
繰り返すと、
And then using the same test set to report the error as though
もしあるパラメータの集合、
selecting your degree of polynomial on the test set, and then reporting the error on
例えばシータ0とかシータ1とかを、
the test set as though that were a good estimate of generalization error.
なんらかのトレーニングセットに対して
That sort of practice is unfortunately many, many people do do it.
フィッティングしたら、
If you have a massive, massive test that is maybe not a terrible thing to do,
そのトレーニングセットにフィットさせたモデルの（そのトレーニングセットに対する）パフォーマンスは
but many practitioners,
新しいサンプルに対して
most practitioners that machine learnimg tend to advise against that.
どれだけうまく一般化出来た仮説と
And it's considered better practice to have separate train validation and
なっているかを予測するのには
test sets.
使えない。 何故ならこれらのパラメータは
I just warned you to sometimes people to do, you know, use the same data for
当然このトレーニングセットにはフィットするだろうから。
the purpose of the validation set, and for the purpose of the test set.
つまりそれらはトレーニングセットに対しては
You need a training set and a test set, and that's good,
良いだろうと思われる。
that's practice, though you will see some people do it.
たとえそのパラメータが、他のサンプルには良くなくても。
But, if possible, I would recommend against doing that yourself.
そしてこのスライドで記述した手順では、